Speaker 1: - Libya. - Gentleman's recognized for five
Speaker 2: minutes. - Thank you, Mr. Chair. First, I'd like to thank the distinguished gentleman from Ohio, Mr. Kucinich, for his tremendous leadership on this issue. There is a growing bipartisan support for this amendment. It's an amendment that gives us the opportunity to stop this unconstitutional war in Libya.
The United
Speaker 2: States has been at war against Libya for nearly
Speaker 3: four months. We have dropped bombs on Libyan buildings.
We
Speaker 3: have flown sorties over Libyan airspace. It has been reported that we have even targeted Gaddafi himself. We are at war. The Constitution vests Congress with the exclusive power to declare war. The President has not attempted to obtain Congress's authorization for the war,
and yet at
Speaker 3: this moment, as we debate on the House floor, the war continues. Instead of
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): following the Constitution and seeking authorization,
the
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): President made strained arguments to justify the continued operation. At first, the operation was supposed to be "limited," as though that undefined term serves as a constitutional escape clause. My constituents certainly would be surprised if Congress established a limited religion or subjected them to limited cruel and unusual
Speaker 3: punishment or quartered soldiers in their houses, but only for a limited
time.
After
Speaker 3: that limited argument ran its course, the President turned to a UN Security Council Resolution and an invitation from an organization of Arab states to justify our involvement. Those organizations were not around at the time the Constitution was written, much less are they listed in its text. The
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): administration now has retreated from its constitutional arguments in public and claims that at least the War Powers Resolution does not forbid the strikes.
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): because we're not involved in "hostilities" against Libya. Imagine that the shoe were on the other foot, that Libya was bombing us. Would we view the Libyan Air Force's bombings of our infrastructure as a hostile act? Of course we would. Last week, a member of the other chamber called the President's arguments "cute." I would use a different term: "embarrassing."
It's
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): embarrassing that the administration attempts to hide behind these transparently strained and flimsy arguments, especially when we're dealing with such a grave issue. But you know what would be more embarrassing? If
Speaker 3: this Congress did nothing. More embarrassing than the President's contortions of the law and disregard for the Constitution would be if Congress, with full
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): knowledge that it was occurring, gave him a pass. In the face of an attack on the Constitution,
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): In the face of an attack on these institutions and our powers as a co-equal branch, we must stand up and say "Stop!" And if we don't, we should be the ones who are embarrassed. The Amash Kucinich Amendment prohibits funds from being used for military force against
Libya. To be
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): clear, I believe that Congress doesn't need to do anything to stop the President from ordering force against Libya, because the President has not received authorization. The use of force is already illegal.
Speaker 4 (higher-pitched voice): However, to reinforce our constitutional position, our amendment says that beginning at the start of the fiscal year on October 1, the armed forces may not drop bombs on Libya or otherwise use military force. Unlike the bill we considered the week before last, our amendment does not implicitly authorize any actions against Libya. It simply says force may not be used because the President has not sought nor has he received authorization for
Speaker 3: force. Please vote yes on the Yamash Kucinich Amendment and defend our constitutional role in war powers. Thank you, Mr. Chair.
The
Speaker 5: gentleman's time has expired. What purpose?